Quirini, Helen; Papers apap102
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Helen Quirini Papers
1898-2010
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Quirini, Helen, 1920-2010
apap102
50.89 cubic ft.
This collection documents the life, work and activism of Helen Quirini of Schenectady, New York. The collection represents Quirini's numerous activities and interests including her early work owning a local market with her brother, her 39 year employment for General Electric, her activism in unions during her employment and retirement, as well as her charitable activities where she pursued civil, housing, pension, women's and senior citizen's rights.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of a small number of select folders marked below.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Helen Quirini in conjunction with the University at Albany, SUNY Department of History's
Schenectady General Electric in the Twentieth Century Project
in November 1999. Additional accessions of records were received from Quirini in 2003, 2004, 2005, and 2006. After Quirini's death in 2010 her nephew, Rudolph Quirini, donated additional materials.
Biographical Sketch
Helen Quirini (1920-2010) was a lifelong resident of Schenectady, New York. She was known for her dedication to numerous causes, such as organized labor, the YWCA of Schenectady, gender and racial equality, social welfare, and local activism. Although Quirini focused primarily on the Capital Region, she also worked for statewide and national causes. She advocated the repeal of the Catastrophic Coverage Act of 1988 and participated in the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom. During her 39 year employment at General Electric (GE) and her 30 year retirement, Quirini advocated for the better treatment of employees and retirees by the management of GE.
Born March 9, 1920 to Marie Ogonowski and Frank K. Quirini, Helen Quirini was the youngest of four children and attended Mont Pleasant High School. On April 1, 1941, at the age of 21, Quirini began working for GE's Schenectady plant doing piece work in the factory. The United States' entrance into World War II interrupted her initial plan to save money in order to attend college. Quirini decided to work at GE throughout the war as a service to her country. By 1945 she had established a pattern of union leadership and community activism that continued for the rest of her life.
At General Electric she joined the Athletic Board, advocated for equal treatment for female employees and organized drives for the local Red Cross. She joined a union, Local 301, which was first affiliated with the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (UE) and later, beginning in 1954, with the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE). Quirini held many executive leadership positions with Local 301, served on numerous labor committees, was a union shop steward and regularly attended union conferences and conventions. Quirini was a vocal force for employee rights, both in boardroom meetings with GE executives and during strikes, protests and work stoppages. In 1953 Quirini mobilized mass protests to advocate for equal pay for women workers at GE. She walked picket lines in all types of weather in support of union solidarity. While employed at GE and as a member of Local 301, Quirini achieved a number of firsts. In 1953, she became the first woman elected chairperson of the special UE-GE Conference Board Meeting, held that year in Chicago. Quirini also was the first woman and hourly representative elected chairperson of the GE Employees Share Fund in 1975.
Quirini was accused of Communist Party affiliation during the McCarthy era because of her union advocacy. She received a subpoena and testified in a pre-hearing that she was not a proponent of Communism, but sought equal rights for all individuals. She testified that she had attended a Communist meeting, and even mentioned seeing "company men" from General Electric there. The case against her was dropped. Quirini filed a Freedom of Information Act request decades later to review the documents held by the FBI from the McCarthy era. Redacted copies of the completed request are available in Series 2.
After her retirement from General Electric in 1980, Quirini became well known for her attempts to win greater benefits for GE retirees through advocacy, shareholder proposals and her annual speech at the GE shareholders meeting. Always wearing a bright T-shirt with the words "GE Brings Good Things to Retirees, Please" Quirini, along with other retirees and their supporters, frequently picketed at General Electric in Schenectady and at the annual shareholder meetings. She served as president of Local 301 Retirees Council and co-founded the GE Retirees Justice Fund. Her highly visible role at shareholder meetings brought her to the attention of Jack Welch, the chairman and CEO of General Electric from 1981-2001. Local playwright Gail George wrote a one-woman play about Quirini's relationship with Welch entitled Helen and Jack.
During her employment for GE, Quirini volunteered for non-union related causes. She joined the YWCA of Schenectady in 1943 and eventually became its president. Through her United Way work with Local 301, she began working with the Refreshing Springs Child Day Care alongside her friend Reverend Georgetta Dix in 1970, where her varied executive duties lasted until 1987.
Quirini continued her activism during her retirement by volunteering for the rights and benefits of seniors and community causes in Schenectady County. She was a member or director of a wide variety of civic and labor organizations, including: the American Association of Retired Persons Chapter 490, Better Neighborhoods Inc., Citizens for Preservation and Revitalization, Human Services Planning Council's Aging Committee, IUE Local 301 Retirees Council, New York State Wide Senior Action Council, Schenectady Council of Senior Citizens, Schenectady County Committee on Health Care Issues, Schenectady County Council of Child Day Care Centers, and Schenectady County Human Rights Commission.
Quirini also was the recipient of many awards. She received the United Way Joseph A. Beirne Award, the YWCA of Schenectady Jefferson Award and the General Electric Gerald L. Phillippe Award. She also received the Patroon award, the highest honor given by the City of Schenectady. Series 1 contains many more awards and related material.
Selections from
Helen Quirini and General Electric: A Personal Memoir of World War II
are made available online through the University at Albany Department of History's History and Media Initiatives website and a copy of the full memoir is found in Series 1.
Quirini also appeared in other publications about unions, women and community activists. Her work for GE retirees garnered her and the pension cause coverage in major newspapers and magazines across the country. In the 1990s, the Schenectady General Electric in the 20th Century Project extensively interviewed Quirini and different periods of her life are documented in articles and student research papers, many of which are available in the collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life, work and activism of Helen Quirini of Schenectady, New York. The collection represents Quirini's numerous activities and interests including her early work owning a local market with her brother, her 39 year employment for General Electric, her activism in unions during her employment and retirement, as well as her charitable activities where she pursued civil, housing, pension, women's and senior citizen's rights.
The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives received this collection through multiple donations. Helen Quirini donated material over approximately 10 years and her nephew Rudy Quirini donated the final materials following Helen Quirini's death in 2010. Many of the papers lacked original order and therefore archivists needed to impose order throughout the collection. Archivists created the series structure to represent Quirini's personal life, employment, labor union work and activism. She held many executive board positions after her retirement and remained an active volunteer and labor rights activist until her death. There is occasional overlap between topics and series such as senior citizens (Series 6, Subseries 5) and pension rights (found in General Electric Series 5).
Quirini spent nearly her entire life in Schenectady, New York. This collection offers a perspective into industrial work during World War II and the life of a female union activist in the mid-20th Century through photographs, diary entries, labor union literature, grievance reports Quirini filed and labor union convention materials. The collection documents the workings of various local organizations through meeting minutes, budgets, correspondence, publications, by-laws, treasurer's reports and other internal documents. Quirini also worked for local chapters of larger organizations. Quirini was active in her local community and corresponded with State and National legislators about a variety of topics, including day care services, labor unions, local government, Schenectady County development, senior citizens' issues and more.
Quirini maintained extensive subject files with clippings, articles, photographs and reports. Also available are collections of publications and newsletters from relevant organizations, such as UE and IUE publications and the New York State Wide Senior Action Council's newsletter.
The audiovisual portion of this collection includes audio and video cassettes, DVDs, CDs, reel-to-reel tapes, 8mm film and 45 RPM record singles.
Please note that not all dates are inclusive.
Related collections in the Department of Special Collections and Archives include the records of IUE-CWA Local 301 (APAP-023), Ralph Boyd Papers (APAP-165, Helen Quirini's friend and fellow advocate for the rights of GE Retirees), Associated Industries of New York State, Inc. (APAP-043), and the New York State Wide Senior Action Council (APAP-111). Issues of the newspapers of Local 301 are available in microfilm, paper, and electronic format in the records of IUE-CWA Local 301 (APAP-023) including special Local 301 publications from the 1966 and 1969 strikes.
Quirini deposited various materials at other repositories including the: Schenectady Public Library (material related to Georgetta Dix) and the NYU Tamiment Libraries and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives. Her nephew Rudolph Quirini also donated materials to the Grems-Doolittle Library at the Schenectady County Historical Society.
Reproductions of items from this collection are available in the exhibit
Documenting Labor Inside and Out: Labor History in New York State's Capital District
.
Separated Materials
Archivists transfered two monographs Precedings: Sixth Annual Convention of the International Union of Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers- CIO and Precedings: Seventh Annual Convention of the International Union of Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers- CIO to the book division of Special Collections. The catalog records for the monograph will be included in the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Biographical, 1940-2010, Undated
Series 2 - Work, Union and Politics, 1933-2007, Undated
Series 3 - Women and Work, 1942-2009, Undated
Series 4 - Labor Newspapers, 1917-1987
Series 5 - General Electric, 1918-2010, Undated
Series 6 - Community Activism, 1898-2010, Undated
Subseries 1 - Human Rights, 1952-2005, Undated
Subseries 2 - YWCA, 1898-2009, Undated
Subseries 3 - Day Care, 1953-2005, Undated
Subseries 4 - Schenectady County Development and Consumerism, 1969-2007, Undated
Subseries 5 - Senior Citizens, 1972-2010, Undated
Subseries 6 - Human Services, 1970-2009, Undated
Subseries 7 - United Way, 1963-2008, Undated
Subseries 8 - Health Care, 1969-2009, Undated
All series, including the subseries in series six, are arranged alphabetically except for series four, Labor Newspapers, which is arranged chronologically by publication.
Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Senior Citizens; Schenectady, New York; Medicine and Health Care; Labor; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women in community organization--United States; Community organization--New York (State) --Schenectady; Pensions--Cost-of-living adjustments--United States; Retirees--New York (State)--Finance, Personal; Labor union locals--New York (State); Labor union meetings--New York (State); Labor union members--New York (State); Labor unions--Recognition--New York (State); Labor unions and communism--New York (State); Women labor union members--New York (State); Strikes and lockouts--New York (State); Older people--New York (State); Memorabilia; Photographs; Testimonies; Speeches; Serials (publications); Financial Records; Histories; Diaries; Awards; Contracts; Audiocassettes; Videocassettes; Quirini, Helen--1920-2010; Welch, Jack, 1935-; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America; International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine, and Furniture Workers; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Labor Union Democracy--United States; New York State-wide Senior Action Council; Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation; New York (State--Public Service Commission
- Biographical, 1940-2010; Undated; 1; 5.2 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes material about Helen Quirini's life and achievements. This series has correspondence, awards and certificates, newspaper articles by and about Quirini and her activism, letters of recommendation, theses, interview transcripts, diaries of her time on the shop floor at General Electric, her memoir, photographs, ephemera and more. This series covers the entirety of Quirini's life and work starting with the Brother Sister Cash Market where she worked with her brother in the late 1930s and early 1940s, her 39 years working at General Electric and then her post-retirement activism. The original order, titling and folder contents were preserved wherever possible. Quirini received a variety of national awards including the Beirne Award from the United Way and the Phillipe Award from General Electric. She also received local accolades such as the Patroon award in her hometown of Schenectady, New York. Included in the award folders are nomination materials, letters of recommendation, resumes, related materials and the awards themselves. This series contains extensive correspondence regarding Quirini's personal life, employment, activism and fundraising. There also are many VHS cassettes of Schenectady City Council meetings which Quirini attended as a citizen. Series 1 covers her activism, awards and achievements as both the subject and author of newspaper articles. Several students also corresponded with Quirini and wrote about her in papers and masters theses. Scholarly publications which predominantly feature Quirini are located in this series. Please see Series 2 and Series 3 for other scholarly writings about unions in general, Local 301 or General Electric.
  - Andy William, Undated (Reel 1)
  - Assorted Material Written by Helen Quirini, 1944-1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1945-2008 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 2)
  - Awards- Assorted Letters of Recommendation and Clippings, 1972-1973; 1975; 1977; 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 3)
  - Awards- Honors and Related Correspondence, 1971-2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 4)
  - Awards- Letter of Recommendation, Certificates and Accolades, 1945; 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 5)
  - Awards- Materials Related to Nomination and Acceptance, 1948-1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 6)
  - Awards- Notification Material, 1970-2006; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 7)
  - Bat-time to 20, Art Linkletter, Kids, Quartet Old Songs, Undated (Reel 2)
  - Bennington Center, Mary Stephanie Hart, 1998 August 23 (Video-tape 1)
  - Bennington Center, Quirini Talks, 1998 August 22 (Video-tape 2)
  - Beirne Award, 1970-1978; 1980; 1987; 2005-2007; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 8)
  - Beirne Award, 1976-1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 9)
  - Beirne Award, 1977-1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 10)
  - Beirne Community Service Award, 1987 (Video-tape 3)
  - Beirne Award-Contents of Scrapbook, 1977; 1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 11)
  - Beirne Award-Correspondence, 1973-1977; 1977-1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 12)
  - Bierne Award Coverage in IUE News, 1978 (Oversized 3, Folder 1)
  - Beirne Award, Dinner at Hunts, Detroit, 1978 (Film 2)
  - Beirne Award-Related Publicity and Notification, Acceptance Speech, Photos, 1977-1978; 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 13)
  - Bill May, Undated (Film 1)
  - Bloom Where You are Planted, Undated (Cassette 1)
  - Boat Trip with Rhoda, 2004; 2005 (Dvd 1)
  - Bob's Pics, 2005 (Cd 1)
  - Boyd, Ralph-Correspondence, 2004; 2006; 2008-2009 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 14)
  - Bread and Roses Certificate, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 15)
  - Brother and Sister Cash Market, 1940 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 16)
  - Brother and Sister Cash Market Advertisements, 1940 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Camille Party, 1958 (Reel 3)
  - Catholic Charities of Schenectady County - Award and Silent Auction Event, 2008; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 17)
  - Central Labor Council Award, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 18)
  - Certificates, 1974-2009; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 19)
  - Certificates of Honors, Awards, 1973-2009; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 20)
  - Cities and Suburbs, 2nd Meeting, Undated (Reel 4)
  - City Council Meeting, 1998 August 25 (Video-tape 4)
  - City Council Meeting, 1998 November 16 (Video-tape 5)
  - City Council Meeting, 1998 November 23 (Video-tape 6)
  - City Council Meeting, 1998 December 28 (Video-tape 7)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 November 09-1999 November 10 (Video-tape 8)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 March 09 (Video-tape 9)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 April 12 (Video-tape 10)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 July 12 (Video-tape 11)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 July 26 (Video-tape 12)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 August 09 (Video-tape 13)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 October 25 (Video-tape 14)
  - City Council Meeting, 1999 December 13 (Video-tape 15)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 April 24 (Video-tape 16)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 June 13 (Video-tape 17)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 July 10 (Video-tape 18)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 July (Video-tape 19)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 August 14 (Video-tape 20)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 August 28 (Video-tape 21)
  - City Council Meeting, 2000 November 14 (Video-tape 22)
  - City Council Meeting, 2002 February 11 (Video-tape 23)
  - City Council Meeting, 2004 February 23 (Video-tape 24)
  - City Council Meeting, 2004 April 12 (Video-tape 25)
  - City Council Meeting, Undated (Video-tape 26)
  - Clippings about Helen Quirini, 1946-2009; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 21)
  - Clippings about the Quirini Family, 1953; 1967; 1969; 1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 22)
  - Clippings by and about Helen Quirini, 1975-1976; 1981; 1987; 1990-1997; 2003-2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 23)
  - Clippings-Congressional Record Article, 1970 May (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 24)
  - Clippings-Regarding Awards and Honors, 1968; 1974-1978; 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 25)
  - Clippings about World War II, Helen Quirini and GE, 1944-1945 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 26)
  - Community Activism-Lists of Accomplishments, Correspondence including Letter of Recommendation and Congratulations, Clippings, 1967-2009; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1945-2007; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1954-1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1944; 1954-1959; 1974; 1978; 1999 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 30)
  - Correspondence Regarding the Achievements of Helen Quirini, 1971-1974; 1984; 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 31)
  - Correspondence with State and National Legislatures, 1983-1990; 1992-1993; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 32)
  - County Meeting, 1999 August 01 (Video-tape 27)
  - County Meeting, 1999 November 09 (Video-tape 28)
  - County Meeting, 2000 February 14 (Video-tape 29)
  - County Meeting, 2000 March 14 (Video-tape 30)
  - County Meeting, 2000 July 24 (Video-tape 31)
  - County Meeting, 2006 December (Video-tape 32)
  - Credit Union Records, ca. 1960s (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 33)
  - D'Amato, Alphonse-Correspondence, 1981-1991 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 34)
  - Diaries-Shop Floor, 1944; Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 35)
  - Diaries-Shop Floor, 1946-1947 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 36)
  - Edna's Party, 1996 April 13 (Video-tape 33)
  - Excerpts from Regional Conference, Undated (Reel 5)
  - Executive Sessions of the Senate Permanent Subcommittee on the Investigations of the Committee on Government Operations, Volumes 1-5, 1953 (Cd 2)
  - Evelyn Birthday, 1960 (Reel 6)
  - Frank Ducci, 1999 (Video-tape 34)
  - Friedan, Betty-Obituary, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 37)
  - General Correspondence, 1954-1981; 1983; 1995-1996; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 1)
  - Girzone, Joseph-Memorial Booklet and Clippings, 1973-2002; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 2)
  - Goodbye to Hank, Undated (Dvd 2)
  - Grad RSDC, Undated (Film 3)
  - Graduation Certificate, 1945 June 25 (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 3)
  - Helen, A Lifetime of Deeds, Undated (Cd 3)
  - Helen Party, 1980 May 17 (Cassette 2)
  - Helen Quirini and General Electric: A Personal Memoir of World War II, 1991; 2001; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 4-5)
  - Helen Quirini Autobiography, Conversations in Car, Lisa Kanneberg, 1991 (Cassette 3)
  - Helen Qurini Interview, Channel 17, 1994 September (Video-tape 35)
  - Helen Quirini Interview by Lisa Kanneberg, 1991 February 01 (Cassette 4-5)
  - Helen Quirini Interview by Lisa Kanneberg, 1991 February 02 (Cassette 6)
  - Helen Quirini Interview by Lisa Kanneberg, 1991 February 03 (Cassette 7)
  - Helen Quirini Interview by Lisa Kanneberg, 1991 December 06 (Cassette 8-9)
  - Helen Qurini, James Carrey, Gerald Zahavi, and Elizabeth Griffin, 1992 February 27 (Cassette 10)
  - History 101 Class, Zahavi/SUNYA, 2004 November 08 (Video-tape 36)
  - History 101 Presentation Images, 2004 November 08 (Cd 4)
  - Homefront and Warfront, Remembering WWII, Undated (Video-tape 37)
  - Honors-Letters in Support of, Lists of Activities and Awards, etc., 1967-2006 (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 6)
  - Horses, Undated (Film 4)
  - Interview with Quirini on WWII, Undated (Dvd 3)
  - Interview Helen Qurini, WWII Civilian, Latham Armory, 2004 August (Video-tape 38)
  - Interview with Helen Qurini on WWII, Latham Armory, 2004 August 31 (Dvd 4)
  - Interview with Professor Gerald Zahavi in History 101 at SUNY Albany, 2004; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 7)
  - Interview with Professor Gerald Zahavi: Unedited Transcript, Drafts, 1982; 1991 (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 8)
  - Jefferson Award, 1970; 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Karen-Mayor of Schenectady, 1978-2010; Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical), Folder 10)